Yaojie Liu

CONTACT Information Department of Computer Science and Engineering,

Michigan State University,

East Lansing, MI 48824, USA

E-mail: liuyaoj1@msu.edu Phone: (614)-886-6885

Web: www.cse.msu.edu/~liuyaoj1/

Job Interests

A full-time position in 2021 Spring in the area of computer vision and deep learning.

RESEARCH INTERESTS Computer Vision, Deep Learning, Face Analysis, Image Synthesis, Biometrics, Low-level Vision, Audio-Visual Modeling, Image Forensic.

EDUCATION

Michigan State University, MI, USA

Ph.D. Candidate in Computer Science, May 2016 - May. 2021 (Expected)

- Dissertation Title: "Face Anti-Spoofing: Detection, Generalization, and Visualization"
- Advisor: Dr. Xiaoming Liu
- Thesis committee: Xiaoming Liu (chair), Anil Jain, Arun Ross, Daniel Morris
- GPA: 3.67/4

The Ohio State University, OH, USA

M.S. in Computer Science, Sep. 2014 - Apr. 2016

- Research Title: "Global and Local Fitting of Facial Landmarks and Action Units (AUs)"
- Advisor: Dr. Aleix Martinez
- GPA: 3.88/4

University of Electronic Science and Technology of China, Sichuan, China

B.E. in Communication Engineering, Sep. 2010 - Apr. 2014

- Dissertation Title: "Image Inpainting"
- Advisor: Dr. Chang Shu
- GPA: 3.92/4

WORKING EXPERIENCES

Bosch Research, Computer Vision Intern

Sunnyvale, CA

Mentor: Dr. Xinyu Huang, Dr. Liu Ren

Research topic: Face Shadow Removal/Relighting

Apple Inc., AI Research Intern

Cupertino, CA

Mentor: Dr. Barry Theobald, Dr. Nicholas Apostoloff

Research topic: Audio-visual Modeling

Michigan State University, Research Assistant

East Lansing, MI

May 2019 - Aug. 2019

May 2020 - Aug. 2020

May 2016 - Now

RESEARCH HIGHLIGHTS

In the area of face anti-spoofing, I lead the R&D at our team, publish 7 papers, 1 under review, release 2 databases, file 1 patent, organize 2 half-day tutorials and 1 full-day demo. The papers receive overall >500 citations, the databases are distributed to >700 research groups, and our code receive ~ 300 stars & 90 forks on GitHub. In U.S. government-organized independent evaluation,

our RGB camera-based face anti-spoofing solution can achieve **98.4%** TDR at **0.2%** FDR and **0.999** AUC. Our research on face anti-spoofing has been covered by MSUToday [News]. Here are some examples of our face anti-spoofing systems [Video].

PUBLICATIONS

I have >600 citations according to **Google Scholar**, and my h-index is 7. (* denotes equal contribution)

Conference Papers

- 1. Yaojie Liu, Xinyu Huang, Ren Liu, Xiaoming Liu, "Facial Foreign Shadow Detection and Removal via Spatio-Temporal Consistency," under review in CVPR 2021.
- Xiaohong Liu, Yaojie Liu, Jun Chen, Xiaoming Liu, "PSSC-Net: Progressive Spatio-Channel Correlation Network for Image Manipulation Detection and Localization," under review in CVPR 2021.
- 3. Yaojie Liu, Jeol Stehouwer, Xiaoming Liu, "On Disentangling Spoof Traces for Generic Face Anti-Spoofing," Proc. European Conference of Commputer Vision (ECCV), 2020. (26% Acceptance Rate) [PDF] [Code] [Short Video] [Long Video]
- 4. Jeol Stehouwer, Amin Jourabloo, **Yaojie Liu**, Xiaoming Liu, "Noise Modeling, Synthesis and Classification for Generic Object Anti-Spoofing," IEEE Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), 2020. (25% Acceptance Rate) [PDF] [Code] [Database] [Short Video]
- 5. Yaojie Liu, Jeol Stehouwer, Amin Jourabloo, Xiaoming Liu, "Deep Tree Learning for Zero-shot Face Anti-spoofing," IEEE Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), 2019. (Oral, Best Paper Finalist, 5.6% Acceptance Rate.) [PDF] [Code] [Database] [Video] [Poster]
- 6. Yaojie Liu*, Amin Jourabloo*, Xiaoming Liu, "Face De-Spoofing: Anti-Spoofing via Noise Modeling," Proc. European Conference of Commputer Vision (ECCV), 2018. (31.8% Acceptance Rate) [PDF] [Code] [Poster]
- 7. Yaojie Liu*, Amin Jourabloo*, Xiaoming Liu, "Learning Deep Models for Face Anti-Spoofing: Binary or Auxiliary Supervision," IEEE Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), 2018. (30% Acceptance Rate) [PDF] [Database] [Poster]
- 8. Yaojie Liu, Amin Jourabloo, William Ren, Xiaoming Liu, "Dense Face Alignment," International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCVW) Workshop on Analysis and Modeling of Faces and Gestures (AMFG), 2017. [PDF] [Code] [Poster]
- 9. Yaojie Liu*, Yousef Atoum*, Amin Jourabloo*, Xiaoming Liu, "Face Anti-Spoofing Using Patch and Depth-Based CNNs," IEEE International Joint Conference on Biometrics (IJCB), 2017. [PDF] [Poster]
- 10. Ruiqi Zhao, Yan Wang, C.F. Benitez-Quiroz, **Yaojie Liu**, A.M. Martinez, "Fast and Precise Face Alignment and 3D Shape Reconstruction from a Single 2D Image." European Conference on Computer Vision Workshop (ECCVW), 2016. [PDF]
- 11. Yaojie Liu, Chang Shu, "A Comparison of Image Inpainting Techniques." International Conference on Graphic and Image Processing (ICGIP), 2015. [Link]

Journal Papers

- 12. Yaojie Liu, Xiaoming Liu, "Physics-Guided Spoof Trace Disentanglement for Generic Face Anti-Spoofing" under review in IEEE Transaction on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (PAMI), 2020.
- 13. Chang Shu, **Yaojie Liu**, "Inpainting: Survey and Experiments" International Journal of Signal Processing, Image Processing and Pattern Recognition, Vol. 9, Issue. 10, pp. 21-36, October 2016. [Link]
- 14. Yaojie Liu, Chang Shu, Zhizhong Fu "Dynamic Gesture Localization and Recognition Algorithm Based on Skeletonization" Electronic Science and Technology, Vol. 3, pp. 005, 2014. (in Chinese) [Link]

Book Chapters

15. Yaojie Liu, Jeol Stehouwer, Amin Jourabloo, Xiaoming Liu, "Presentation Attack Detection for Face in Mobile Phones" Selfie Biometrics, Ajita Rattani, Reza Derakhahani, and Arun Ross, Eds, Springer-Verlag, 2019. [PDF]

PATENTS

Yaojie Liu, Amin Jourabloo, Xiaoming Liu, "Improved Spoof Detection for Facial Recognition," U.S. Serial No. 62/626,486, filed on Feb 05, 2018.

Honors and Awards

• ECCV 2020 Outstanding Reviewer Award (215 selected from 2,830 reviewers)	
• College of Engineering Dissertation Completion Fellowship, MSU	2020
• CVPR 2019 Best Paper Finalist (45 selected from 1,294 accepted papers)	2019
• Honorable Mention, Engineering Graduate Research Symposium, MSU	2018
• College of Engineering Distinguished Fellowship, MSU	2016
• Best Bachelor Thesis Award, UESTC	2014
• First Rank, People's Scholarship for Excellent Student, China	2013
• Second Rank, People's Scholarship for Excellent Student, China	2012
• Research fund from Institute of Electronic Science and Technology, UESTC	2012
• Research fund from Undergraduate Innovation Foundation, UESTC	2011
• First Rank, People's Scholarship for Excellent University Student, China	2011

Professional Services

Co-Organizer/Lecturer

- Half-day Tutorial, "Secure the Face System: Recent Advances on Detecting Face Spoof Attacks and Digital Face Manipulation" (IJCB), 2020 [Session1] [Session2] [Session3]
- Half-day Tutorial, "Face Anti-Spoofing: Past, Present and Future" International Conference on Biometrics: Theory Applications and Systems (BTAS), 2019 [Session1] [Session2] [Session3]

• Full-day Demo, "Real-time Face Anti-spoofing System" @ IEEE Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), 2018. [Link]

Conference Reviewer

• Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)	2019-2021
• International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV)	2019
• European Conference of Commputer Vision (ECCV)	2020
• Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)	2020
• AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI)	2020-2021
• Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV)	2021
• Asian Conference of Computer Vision (ACCV)	2020
\bullet International Conference on Biometrics: Theory Applications and Systems (BTAS)	2018
• IAPR International Conference On Biometrics (ICB)	2019
• International Conference on Multimedia and Expo (ICME)	2020-2021
• Chinese Conference on Pattern Recognition and Computer Vision (PRCV)	2019-2020

Journal Reviewer

• IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI)	$\boldsymbol{2020}$	
• IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP)	2019 - 2020	
• IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics and Security (TIFS)	2019-2020	
• Computer Vision and Image Understanding (CVIU)	2019 - 2020	
• Neurocomputing	2019-2020	
• Journal of Electronic Imaging (JEI)	2020	
• Image and Vision Computing	2020	
• IEEE Transactions on Biometrics, Behavior, and Identity Science (TBIOM)	2020	
• ACM Transactions on Multimedia Computing, Communications, and Applications (TOMM) 2019		
• IET Computer Vision	2019	
• IEEE Access	2019	
• Journal of Computer Science and Technology (JCST)	2018	

Mentoring

- Xiaohong Liu (Ph.D. in C.S., 2020, McMaster University)
- Xiaohan Zhang (B.S. in C.S., 2017, Michigan State University)
- William Ren (High School Student, Summer 2016, Summer 2017)

$\overline{}$	n.,		
	Ι'Α΄	LI	ζS

- Invited talk, Sichuan University, China. Jan. 2020 "Face Anti-Spoofing: Detect, Visualize, and Generalize"
- Invited talk, University of Electronic Science and Technology of China, China. **Jan. 2020** "Face Anti-Spoofing: Detect, Visualize, and Generalize"
- Invited talk, MSU/ND vision workshop, Notre Dame IN.

 "Deep Tree Learning for Zero-shot Face Anti-spoofing"
- Oral Presentation, CVPR.

 "Deep Tree Learning for Zero-shot Face Anti-spoofing"
- Invited talk, Midwest vision workshop, Chicago IL.

 "Dense Face Alignment"

 Apr. 2017

SKILLS

- Programming Language: Python, C/C++, Java, Git, Bash, HTML, SQL, R, LATEX, Lisp
- Operating Systems: Linux, MacOS, Windows
- Signal Processing: Matlab
- Computer Vision Library: OpenCV
- Deep Learning: Tensorflow, PyTorch, MatConvNet, Caffe.